Eshwen Bhal

PHD STUDENT

62A St Pauls Road, Bristol, United Kingdom. BS8 1LP

📕 +44 (0) 78414 09961 | 🗷 eshwen.bhal@bristol.ac.uk | 🖸 eshwen | 😾 ebhal | 🛅 eshwen-bhal-714557195 | 😘 eshwen.bhal

Profile ____

I am a final year PhD student in particle physics, searching for dark matter using big data from the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) as part of the CMS experiment at CERN. This involves statistical analysis of large datasets, primarily in Python, and solving wide ranging problems from physics to programming standpoints. Additional responsibilities have included detector-related expertise and software development, teaching undergraduates and doing public outreach. Aside from work, I partake in many activities such as taekwondo, weight lifting, hiking and skiing.

Education _

University of Bristol Bristol Bristol

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY IN PHYSICS

Sep. 2016 - Present

- Thesis title: Hadronic Dark Matter Searches at CMS at 13 TeV Under supervision of H. Flächer. Expected submission in April 2020
- Postgraduate student representative for the particle physics group, 2019–20 Role in the Student-Staff Liaison Committee for the School of Physics
- CERN, Geneva, Switzerland Long term attachment, Oct. 2017 Mar. 2019
- $\textbf{- Calorimeter Layer-2 on call expert} \ \text{and} \ \textbf{Level-1 Trigger shifter}, \\ \textbf{Geneva, Switzerland} \ \textit{Additional responsibilities at CERN} \\ \textbf{- Calorimeter Layer-2 on call expert} \ \textbf{- Calorimeter Layer-2 on} \ \textbf{- Calorimeter Layer-$

University of Exeter Exeter, United Kingdom

MASTER OF PHYSICS WITH HONOURS IN PHYSICS WITH ASTROPHYSICS. AWARD: FIRST CLASS (77 %)

Sep. 2012 – Jul. 2016

- Dissertation title: **Simulations of Exoplanet Light Curves** *Under supervision of T. Harries*
- Recipient of a **Dean's Commendation**, 2016 In recognition of outstanding achievement at the fourth stage of my degree
- Recipient of a **Physics Award**, 2015 Being one of the three students with the highest marks at the third stage of my degree
- Recipient of a **Dean's Commendation**, 2014 In recognition of outstanding achievement at the second stage of my degree
- Recipient of a **Physics Award**, 2013 Being one of the three students with the highest marks at the first stage of my degree
- Recipient of a **Dean's Commendation**, 2013 In recognition of outstanding achievement at the first stage of my degree

Monmouth Comprehensive School

Monmouth, United Kingdom

Sep. 2005 - Aug. 2012

SECONDARY SCHOOL QUALIFICATIONS

- **A Level**, 2011–12 Biology (A*), Mathematics (A*), Physics (B), Chemistry (AS Level) (B)
- **Open University**, 2012 Introducing Astronomy (10 credit course)
- GCSE, 2010 10 including English Language and Mathematics at grades A* (4) to A (6)
- WJEC Key Skill, 2010 Communication (Level 2)

Skills ____

Data analysis

- The primary focus of my PhD concerns statistical analysis of large (multi-terabyte) datasets collected by the CMS experiment from the Large Hadron Collider.
- · Developed analysis software in Python and C++, using modern data science tools and distributed computing.
- Visualisation with ROOT and matplotlib. Formal presentations of results with LaTeX and Microsoft PowerPoint.

Collaboration

• Belonging to several working groups of around a dozen people as well as a wider collaboration of over 4,000 people.

Problem solving

• Predominant component of a physics degree. As an undergraduate, conducted more traditional pen-and-paper problem solving in many topics. As a PhD student, wrote code to solve physics problems numerically and perform data analysis.

Multitasking

• Often working on multiple projects at once with different working groups during PhD.

Organisation

• Coordinating different aspects of analyses in my PhD, meticulously documenting programming instructions and procedures of analysis components.

Communication

- Presented formally in my PhD at all levels: regular working group updates, research group and collaboration-wide talks, and several conference posters and talks.
- Participated in outreach to the public at the CERN Open Days 2019 and at @Bristol.

Experience _____

University of Bristol Bristol, United Kingdom

COMPUTING DEMONSTRATOR

Oct. 2019 - Present

• Teaching third year undergraduate students Python and its applications for numerically solving physics problems. Also involves formal marking of assignments and providing feedback.

University of BristolBristol, United Kingdom

MATHEMATICS TUTOR

Jan. 2017 - May 2017

• Taught mathematics for physicists to first year undergraduate students. Also involved formal marking of problem sheets, discussions with the students, and teaching concepts for subsequent assignments.

Publications _____

2020	Searches for semi-visible jets in proton-proton collisions at \sqrt{s} = 13 TeV in hadronic final states	In preparation
2020	Search for an invisibly decaying Higgs boson in proton-proton collisions at \sqrt{s} = 13 TeV in final states with	In preparation
	jets and missing transverse momentum	
2018	Search for natural and split supersymmetry in proton-proton collisions at \sqrt{s} = 13 TeV in final states with jets	JHEP
	and missing transverse momentum	

Conference talks & posters _____

CMS UK Conference, Searches for semi-visible jets in hadronic final states	Oxfordshire, UK
University of Bristol PGR Conference, Search for dark matter via an invisibly decaying Higgs boson at CMS	Bristol, UK
Institute of Physics HEPP and APP Conference, Combined search for an invisibly decaying Higgs boson in	London, UK
hadronic channels at 13 TeV with CMS	London, on
LHCP Conference , The CMS Level-1 jet and energy sum triggers in the LHC Run-II	Bologna, Italy
University of Bristol PGR Conference, Dark matter searches at CMS at 13 TeV	Bristol, UK
	University of Bristol PGR Conference, Search for dark matter via an invisibly decaying Higgs boson at CMS Institute of Physics HEPP and APP Conference, Combined search for an invisibly decaying Higgs boson in hadronic channels at 13 TeV with CMS LHCP Conference, The CMS Level-1 jet and energy sum triggers in the LHC Run-II

References _____

Available on request.